Guide to the Alexander Orr Vietor Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alexander Orr Vietor collection
1774-1956
1815-1867
MS 542
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.25
The collection consists of ships' logs, nineteenth-century cargo manifests of Connecticut ships on fishing voyages, and the papers of ships sailing to the West Indies for rum and sugar and to the Antarctic on sealing expeditions. Also included are miscellaneous legal documents related to ships and shipping and a group of ten letters to Captain George W. Lee or to members of his family (1811-1833). Among the writers is Asa Fitch. Charts, writings on voyages to the Antarctic, including an essay by Alexander O. Vietor, copies of "The Voyage of the Huron and the Huntress" by Edouard A. Stackpole and a small amount of Vietor's correspondence concerning the logbook of the ship, Huron, complete the collection.
Vietor, Alexander O.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alexander O. Vietor, 1940-1956.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Logbook of the ship Huron of New Haven, Connecticut is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 21 instead of originals.
Biographical / Historical
Alexander O. Vietor (1913-1981): associate of naval architecture firm of Cox & Stevens in New York, 1937-1940; in 1941 became assistant to Yale University director of Art Gallery; in 1943 named curator of maps at Yale; from 1948-1950, secretary of Yale Council on Libraries and Museums.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of ships' logs, nineteenth-century cargo manifests of Connecticut ships on fishing voyages, and the papers of ships sailing to the West Indies for rum and sugar and to the Antarctic on sealing expeditions. Also included are miscellaneous legal documents related to ships and shipping and a group of ten letters to Captain George W. Lee or to members of his family (1811-1833). Among the writers is Asa Fitch. Charts, writings on voyages to the Antarctic, including an essay by Alexander O. Vietor, copies of "The Voyage of the Huron and the Huntress" by Edouard A. Stackpole and a small amount of Vietor's correspondence concerning the logbook of the ship, Huron, complete the collection.
Existence and Location of Copies
Logbook of the ship Huron of New Haven, Connecticut, is available on microfilm, (3 reels, 35mm.) from Scholarly Resources, Inc., Wilmington, Delaware.
Shipping -- Connecticut; Voyages and travels; Antarctica; United States -- Commerce -- West Indies; West Indies -- Commerce -- United States; Logs (records); Ships' papers; Fitch, Asa, 1809-1879; Lee, George W.; Stackpole, Edouard A., 1905-; Vietor, Alexander O.; Huron (Ship)
- Inventory
  - Logbook of the ship Huron of New Haven, Connecticut, 1821 January 18-1822 April 27 (Box 1, Reel 2)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Logbook of the ship Huron of New Haven, Connecticut, is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 21 instead of originals.
  - Correspondence of A. O. Vietor re: the logbook of the ship Huron, 1952-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "New Haveners in the Antarctic" by A. O. Vietor [manuscript], 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Voyage of the Huron and the Huntress by Edouard A. Stackpole [two copies], 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous writings by various authors re: the discovery of Antarctica, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings from the New Haven Register re: A. O. Vietor and the logbook of the ship, 1956 March 25 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chart of the North and South Atlantic Ocean, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "A Statement showing the location, latitude, longitude, elevation... of the light-houses in Long Island Sound...", 1830 July 15 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Petitions and depositions to Judge William Bristol on behalf of Samuel G. Stanton (ADD II), 1840 November (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Logbook of the ship Ploughboy (ADD III), 1803 June 9-1804 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous repair and other receipts forvariousvessels (ADD IV), 1774, 1814, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Transcript from the journal of the U.S. Revenue Cutter Wolcott (ADD V), 1838-1841 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Three letters to Peter Force (ADD VI), 1815, 1827, 1834 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers re: ships and shipping (ADD VI), 1799-1833 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notes to various persons from Alexander James Dallas (1791-1844) (ADD VII), 1835 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letter with bill of lading to Messrs. Seth Low & Co. from Robert Brookhouse (ADD VII), 1838 July 5 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Order to Messrs. Baldwin & Co. from Wichelhausen & Achelis (ADD VII), 1839 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Compendio de Naveg[aci]on [manuscript textbook?] (ADD VIII), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Transcript journal of Spanish naval vessels [manuscript textbook?], undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Two bills of lading issued by Thomas Lockyer Co. (ADD X), 1866 March 28, 1867 December 5 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Five account sheets of various sheets (ADD X), 1824-1832 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ten letters to members of the family of Capt. George W. Lee (ADD X), 1811-1833 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fourteen circulars from the Clerk of the Marine Records to the collector at New Haven, Connecticut (ADD X), 1818-1829 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bills and receipts mostly re: Paul Pinkham of Nantucket, Massachusetts (ADD XIII), 1788-1797 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "The Bloody Story of the Whaleship Globe," by Steele Barhydt, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous bills of sale, reports, certificates, and manifests of various vessels (ADDS I, IX, X), 1782-1829 (Box 3)